[music]
Hey, welcome back everybody. Thanks
everybody. [cheering]
Ladies and gentlemen,
my guest tonight [applause] is a stage
and screen legend. You've known as
Hamlet, Prospero, Magneto, and of
course, Gandalf. [screaming] He now
[cheering]
stars in a new play called Anarch.
Please welcome back to the late show Ian
Mckllen.
>> [cheering]
[music]
>> Heat
up [music]
here.
[music]
>> [cheering]
>> How lovely to see you again, Ian.
>> Doing well, I hope to be here. Yes.
>> Yes. That's for you. Yes, sir. That's
for you. This is mine,
>> Jin.
>> Yes. Yes. Exactly. The bee feeder. Just
as you asked. Now,
before we get to uh anything else, happy
this year's 25th anniversary of the
greatest trilogy of all time. [cheering]
to celebrate. You recently got together
with The Hobbits for an Empire magazine
cover.
>> Yes.
>> And did you get together to com to
compare how your tattoos have aged?
Because you all
>> you all have the Elvish Nine tattoo on
your shoulder right there.
>> Yes. And I only see it upside down, you
know.
>> Oh, yes.
>> And uh although the right way up it
spells nine for the fellowship in
Elvish. What would that word be?
>> Uh Nino.
I don't know. I don't know what N.
>> Yeah. Do you know what the word nine is
in Elvish?
>> No.
>> But upside down is which is the way I
read it. It spells spells Gucci.
[laughter]
>> The father, the son, the house of Gucci.
All right. Now, will you sir this very
quickly here? I understand when you like
first got the role, you hadn't read the
books.
>> No, I was rather ashamed that I hadn't.
I didn't know really know what they were
talking about when they came to ask me
to be in it. And there wasn't a script
to read. They're just a few designs for
the scenery and so on. And of course,
ever since I members of the family and
friends and total strangers come up to
me and tell me that they have like you
read the books and some even boast I
read Lord of the Rings every year. Are
you one of those?
>> Um, [laughter]
every year would be a little light.
>> All right.
[cheering]
[applause]
Well, on my first day in uh Wellington
in um New Zealand, I was taken out to
dinner by Peter Jackson, who you know is
a very sociable fellow. And that's where
I met for the first time the four
adorable hobbits.
>> Sure. Yeah.
>> And the glamorous three, Aragorn,
Boromir, and Legolus.
[laughter]
Uh and a rival wizard who was sitting
next to me at supper. Um, Christopher
Aendini Lee, veteran of 200 movies, in
10 of which he played Dracula.
>> Yes.
>> And during the soup, he turned to me
with that dreadful piercing look and
those dark eyes as if he was
contemplating a virgin neck. And he said
to me, "I read Lord of the Rings every
year."
And then the killer. I've always thought
I should play Gandalf.
>> That's a fine. How do you do? [laughter]
>> But he was a very nice man indeed. And I
think that was a joke. But maybe not.
>> Maybe not. Um I understand. Uh
looking back
that first day on set was a rather
unusual scene for you to shoot on the
first day. Well, it was the very first
scene of my character uh arriving in
Hobbiton
>> uh with the hat which kept blowing off
and had to be fixed with a piece of
elastic which I hope you didn't see.
>> Uh but that was fine. Uh but the next
day I was filming the very last scene of
the third movie when I by which time I
was Gandalf the White about whom I knew
very little. And you're leaving?
>> And I'm leaving these four small people.
And I I said to Peter Jackson, "Do I
know these guys?" He said,"Yes."
[laughter]
I said, "Do I like them?" He said, "Yes.
Yes. You've been through quite a lot
with them." So I looked at them rather
bindingly, but if you look back at that
particular shot, you'll see there is
absolutely nothing happening on my face
at all. I thought that was the safest
thing to do. do nothing.
>> We could just project onto you.
>> And you can project what you want. Yeah.
>> Well, you fooled us.
>> Good.
>> Now, I was so happy to hear that you're
going to be reprising the role of
Gandalf in uh The Hunt for Golem, which
is the next film Andy Circus is
directing. I know that you really can't
tell us anything about the story. I
understand that. But can you you can can
you tell us when you start filming?
uh I think in July, which is unfortunate
because it's winter down there in uh New
Zealand, and I'm not sure that I want to
be out there in the wind and the rain,
>> but we'll be indoors probably most of
the time. Yes. And I I put on the the
pointy hat and the the beard.
>> Yeah.
>> And the nose. Yeah. Sure.
>> And the eyebrows.
>> Yes.
>> And the mustache. Yeah.
>> Oh, dear. And the gloves, I dare say. I
don't know.
>> Yes. Have you seen the photos that
people have have sort of caught you
wearing things that are not canon? Like
there's a moment when you're fighting in
Minister. If you look, you've got your
watch on.
And there's another moment, I think it's
in Helms, look down, you've got like
trainers on, you've got sneakers on.
Well, if people had looked closely at
the movies that they would have realized
that in in my voluminous gown
>> Yes.
>> Uh I had a pocket to put the complete
works of Tolken uh which I always
referred to each day before shooting
particular.
>> Did you really have the books?
>> Yes. And you can you can quite clearly
see the outline of a book as I'm going
along.
>> But then that's all right. Gandalf
Gandalf right there. Annie Circus is
directing uh the new film. What do you
look for in a director?
>> Because I'm looking for a new gig and
[laughter]
If I were to direct you as G, what are
you looking what are you looking for
from a director? I
>> I would ask you what I have asked of
every film director I've ever worked
with.
Uh please will you teach me how to act
in front of the camera and none of them
has ever done that. So if if if you're
willing to Yeah, sure. You're wrong.
>> Ready? Here. I got it for you. Ready?
[applause]
>> I got two pieces of advice for you. One
is talk loud and fast and worry about
the art later.
>> Yes.
>> And the second one is the shortest
distance between two points is learn
your lines.
>> Ah yes.
>> Are you a quick study?
>> Oh no no not anymore.
>> I used to be. I I can't remember having
to learn lines when I used to do a
different play every two weeks. But now
I do every a play once every two years.
It get does get more difficult. You you
you're not only re you know going back
to Gandalf, you also are going to go
back as Magneto in Avengers Doomsday.
[cheering]
[applause]
So that's fun. You get you get you get
you get to be like the good guy and the
bad guy. You got the hot side hot and
the cool side cool. Now, I I don't
always always understand the story of
these movies that I'm in.
>> Neither do I, but it doesn't really
matter.
>> But but in this one, I don't think I'm
uh spoiling anything by saying that uh
um Magneto destroys New Jersey.
>> New Jersey.
>> I'm sorry about that. New Jersey. Oh,
wow. My fault.
So, I'm I'm standing up uh pretending to
do that and the wind is blowing in my
hair and I and and I'm putting on a
fierce look and I'm trying to be
magnetic
and uh
the director of the loud speaker says,
"Ian, look more furious."
>> [laughter]
[cheering]
[applause]
>> He then said, he said, "Shout
something." I I SAID, "WHAT DO I SHOUT?"
HE HE SAID, "Shout the worst thing you
could possibly think of." So I said,
"MAAGO
[cheering]
>> [applause]
>> GOOD.
>> Will I be allowed back in the country?
>> Will you be allowed back in the country?
>> Yeah.
>> No, no guarantees.
>> I don't think I'm the right person to
ask for that.
>> Um, next uh next year will be the 60th
anniversary of your Broadway debut in
the play The Promise.
>> That's right.
>> Okay. So, I'm curious. What were your
first impressions? [applause]
I can't believe it taking that long to
get to Broadway. What were your first
impressions of of coming to New York and
and and doing a play?
>> Well, I was so excited. I was met by my
agent at what is now JFK.
[clears throat]
Uh and we drove in a taxi into Time
Square. And at that time, the traffic
moved around Time Square in both
directions.
>> Yeah.
>> Motorcars.
>> But in the middle there's a statue of
George M. Cohen, one of the great heroes
of Broadway. And there was a guy
standing by the statue urinating on it.
And I thought, my god, these critics,
they get everywhere, don't they?
[applause]
[cheering]
>> Now,
>> so it was a it was a wild it was a wild
place. You didn't go down 42nd Street.
You you peeped down because you knew
there were terrible things going on down
there.
>> Unless you wanted to be part of the
terrible anyone down 42nd Street. And I
don't know that it's improved by being
so respected. You can't even smoke now
in Times Square.
>> You can't?
>> No.
>> Wow.
>> Yeah.
>> Cigarettes.
>> Anything. I [laughter]
>> If you think people aren't smoking in
New York, you need to get out more
>> because [laughter] I get a contact high
getting out of the car and going to the
cab.
>> Okay. So, um you're now in a starring in
a play called Anarch, which is called a
mixed reality play. What is that
different from a film or or a play? Oh,
in every possible way. You sit in a room
with a lot of other people as members of
an audience, but you're by yourself in
your seat and you put on a pair of
glasses,
not unlike these. I mean, perfectly
ordinary glasses they seem to be. You
pop them on. Oh. Oh. And in front of you
are four chairs that weren't there when
you didn't have them on.
>> And the lights go down and into these
four chairs come four people, one of
whom is me.
And the play starts and these four
characters talk directly to you and you
would swear that they were real people.
They really were there and that you
could touch them,
but you can't because they're not there.
But it's it's not like watching a film.
They're not on a screen that it's
there's no no AI involved. It's just a
technique that allows
it. [laughter] I can't describe it any
more than that. We look as if we're
really there. And what's marvelous about
it is that what I like most about live
theater is the direct communication with
the audience that they know I'm here,
you're there, and there's only a bit of
space between us. In in this case, I'm
not there, but I'm even more real than
if I were on a stage in front of you. I
can't explain it any more than that. The
script's written by Simon Stevens, who
is the one of the great playwrights in
United Kingdom at the moment. It lasts
just about an hour. And uh I don't know
whether it's the future, but it's
certainly not the past. It's uh it's
extraordinary.
>> Well, it sounds fascinating. [applause]
[applause]
>> The play deals with themes of death and
the afterlife. Yes. And and you've said
that every role you take on these days,
you you keep in mind that it could
possibly be your last role. And I'm
curious how like this far into your
career as opposed to say 60 years ago uh
when you were performing, how does it
change your does that in any way change
your approach to a role?
>> There's nothing I
enjoy more
than uh acting
and by not so much in movies but in the
theater.
And there you are where I have so often
sat myself because I I I go to the
theater all the time. But there we are.
We're in the same room, the same space,
and something happens. There is a a
collective
uh happening. I speak, you listen, you
laugh, you cry, you you're moved, you're
you're you're stimulated in some way.
And at the end of the evening, you can
turn to a total stranger next to you and
say, "Well, what did you think of the
show?"
And if it's worked, [applause]
I if if it's worked, you you'll never
forget it.
And I want to go on being part of that
as long as I can as an audience and as a
performer.
And uh so although I made five movies
last year, I think this year I'm going
to be more involved with live
performance.
>> Do you remember the first play you saw
or your earliest memory of going to the
live theater?
Oh, a lot. I The first Shakespeare I saw
was McBth done by some amateurs in the
north of England. First player I saw was
Peter Pan.
Will there be a real crocodile?
Will they really fly?
Well, we'll have to wait and see.
Trouble was I could see them and I could
see the wires. It was um
[laughter]
>> and where did that go from, oh this is
something I enjoy to something this is
something I must do?
>> Well, it was the thrill of going to
Peter Pan eventually. I mean when Peter
Pan said do you believe in fairies?
>> Yes.
[laughter]
I was only three years old, but I
clapped away
and uh answer I've been clapping ever
since, of course. Uh
we had to leave early to get the train
back home and we were pushing along uh
the seats there and we got to the door
there. I look back at the stage,
Neverland, and at the back there was
nothing but starlight
>> lights in the black
curtain. And I can remember saying to
myself, I I'm I'm coming back.
>> I want more of this.
>> But it wasn't about me being on the
stage. No, I wanted to find out how do
you make starlight?
>> Where do the wires go?
Uh, and that's why I became a amateur
actor was to get on stage to find out
what it was like to be backstage.
And I still find the same. It was a
thrill just standing there in the wings
there knowing that here there was a show
going on. There there's not a show going
on. [laughter]
Where is that line?
>> I know the tension, the sort of the hot
and the cold, the two sort of
thermocines between those two is a
wonderful kind of exquisite tension if
you get to popping back forth. Here you
are in a bit of live theater and as much
fun as it is watching your show as I do
night after night and thank God.
[cheering]
[screaming]
[applause]
[cheering]
>> If I if I want to know the truth about
what's going on in uh American politics,
I watch the Steven Colbear show.
[cheering]
[applause]
But tonight I am here. Well, it's
actually happening.
And this is live theater that you're
doing.
>> Sure. And live music.
>> And live music. Thank goodness.
[applause]
>> It happens that a lot of people are
going to watch it because it's being
televised. But we all had this secret.
We were here.
[cheering]
>> We were here.
I don't know. I love your I love the
description. I love your description of
yourself as that little boy who wanted
to who saw those lights and wanted to be
back not on stage but in this theater. I
tell young performers sometimes or just
people who want to who interns here,
I'll often say to them, I said, "I have
some good news for you. Um, there's a
place for you in show business, but it
may not be where you think it is."
>> No. If you want to be when I was young,
if I if I could go in a theater, even if
the theater was empty, I'd like to go in
the theater and just sit down and be in
the theater. I felt uh uh held by it. I
felt safe in there. Or rather, not safe,
but I felt like I belonged, even if we
were going to try something dangerous. I
felt like this was that there was a
storm going on outside, but this was a
safe harbor where all of us were going
to do something together. Even if I tore
the tickets or painted the sets or did
the sound or swept up, I would do
anything when I was a young man to just
be in that theater every night. And by
hook or by crook, this is what I ended
up doing.
>> But the goal was to stay in that
building.
>> Yeah.
>> And I tell young people, it's like have
that in your heart.
>> Want to go help that thing because
theater needs everything and show
business needs everything that humans do
so we can reflect what humans do.
>> Yes. You know, you can paint the sets,
you can drive the van, you can pay the
checks, anything. Everyone's in the
show. [applause]
>> And it is happening now.
>> Yes.
>> This is not recorded for you.
>> This is it.
>> No, [cheering and applause]
>> he's real. You're real. I'm real.
>> That's And I think that's [music] And I
think that's the good news. I think
that's one of the good news of sort of
the coming AI revolution is that I think
there's going to be a little bit of a
spring back to wanting to go see
something live so that you know that's a
real human saying real human words to
another human written by a human about
what it's like to be human for other
humans.
[cheering]
Uh uh I I was I was just in Chicago uh
and uh doing a fundraiser for the uh
Chicago Shakespeare Theater and uh I I'm
met some kids there and did a little
little show for them and and I said look
before you go can I just tell you that
that there was a song written by uh
Rogers and Hammerstein. Incidentally
this theater where we are now was built
as did you know by Oscar Hammerstein.
>> Yeah. And uh the song goes, "Some
enchanted evening,
you may see a stranger.
You may see a stranger across a crowded
room. And somehow you know, you know,
even then that somehow you'll meet her
again and again. Not if you're on your
phone, you won't. [cheering]
[music]
>> [cheering]
[cheering and applause]
>> We we've we've got to we've got to go
here in in just a moment. But before you
before you go, I want to I want to talk
to you about Shakespeare because you're
[snorts] in in in my light the the
greatest Shakespearean actor uh that
I've ever seen. Sorry Derek Jackabe.
Sorry Mark Ryland. Sorry Judy Dench.
It's this guy. Um but as the as the goat
of of of Shakespeare uh one of the
reasons why you've got this remarkable
career, one of the things that's a
highlight of this career is that and
explain to me what this means. You are
one of the only living actors who has
premiered a Shakespearean role.
>> You you originated the role.
>> I did.
>> What was that? And how you look
fantastic for 400. [laughter]
[applause]
>> Um
Shakespeare uh wrote many plays, 37 of
them by himself, but he also contributed
to other people's shows. uh and uh one
of the speeches he wrote for a play
called Thomas Moore
uh has been preserved and it's the only
sample of his actual handwriting of some
of the words of a play by him and it's
not in the Fulier Library. It's in the
British Library. You can see it. It's on
display there in London. And it happened
that the play was never performed during
Shakespeare's lifetime because it was
thought to be a bit sedicious.
It had its actual premiere on stage in
1964 was the 400th anniversary of
Shakespeare's birth and I played Thomas
Moore. So you are looking at a man
[applause]
who uh who created a part by William
Shakespeare.
>> So this is handwritten. They know this
is his handwriting of this monologue
that you did
>> of a of a speech you probably don't know
but you ought to because it's a
wonderful
>> I don't know that. Would you mind? Would
you mind doing it for us?
[cheering]
[applause]
>> No, I wouldn't. I I wouldn't mind
because you'll enjoy it.
>> All right. Live theater.
>> Yes.
>> What's it [cheering] what's what's
what's the setting? What's it take place
in the play?
>> Uh it it this it's all happening 400
years ago. Uh and in London, there's a
there's a riot happening. There's a mob
out in the streets and they're
complaining about the the presence of
strangers in London, by which they mean
the recent uh immigrants who've arrived
there. And they're shouting the odds and
complaining and saying that the
immigrants should be sent back home
wherever they came from. And uh the
authorities send out this young lawyer,
Thomas Moore, to put down the riot,
which he does in two ways. one by saying
that you can't riot like this. It's
against the law. So, shut up, be quiet.
Uh and also being by Shakespeare with an
appeal uh to their humanity.
So, in order to set it up, we really
need somebody to shout that the
strangers should be removed. Could
someone do that?
>> Grant them removed.
And grant that this your noise hath chid
down all the majesty of England. Imagine
that you see the wretched strangers,
their babies at their backs, with their
poor luggage, plotting to the ports and
coasts for transportation,
and that you sit as kings in your
desires, authority quite silenced by
your brawl, and you in rough of your
opinions clothed. What had you got?
I'll tell you,
you had taught how insulence and strong
hands should prevail, how order should
be quelled.
And by this pattern, not one of you
should live an aged man. For other
ruffians, as their fancies wrought with
self-same hands, self-reason, and
self-right,
would shark on you, and men like
ravenous fishes feed on one another.
You'll put down strangers, kill them.
Cut their throats,
possess their houses.
Oh, desperate as you are, wash your foul
minds with tears.
And those same hands that you, like
rebels, lift against the peace, lift up
for peace. And your unreverent knees,
make them your feet to kneel to be
forgiven.
And say now the king,
as he is clement, if the offender mourn,
should so much come too short of your
great trespasses but to banish you
with thee would you go?
What country by the nature of your error
should give you harbor? Go you to France
or Fllanders, to any German province,
Spain or Portugal, anywhere that not
adheres to England. Why?
You must needs be strangers.
Would you be pleased
to find a nation of such barbarous
temper that breaking out in hideous
violence would not afford you an abroad
on earth?
Quet their detested knives against your
throats.
spurn you like dogs, and like as if that
God owned not, nor made not you, nor
that the elements were not all
appropriate to your comforts, but
chartered unto them.
What would you think
to be thus used?
This
is the strangest case and this your
mountedness
in humanity.
William Shakespeare 400 years ago.
[cheering]
[cheering and applause]
Thank you.
Tickets [cheering] to an art are
available now in the town. Everybody,
we'll be right back with a performance
by Earth.
[music]
>> [cheering]